people think that having a disability is
a barrier but that's not a way I see it
you can catch up with friends ready you
can capture a moment with your family
Sall face focus long and you can start
the day bright and early you can take a
trip to somewhere new
you can concentrate on every word of the
story a bird began to sing jack opened
his eyes you can take the long way home
or edit a film like this one
when technology is designed for everyone
it lets anyone do what they love
including me
a simple click on the switch it's all it
takes the simple switch activations have
opened up my world the world that was
difficult for me before because my body
doesn't work like everyone else sisters
and this world places barriers in front
of me making access difficult if not
impossible some barriers are meant to
come down and I am here to tear them
them I am a video editor and storyteller
and advocate and activist an artist
so what Sadie didn't tell you is that
she was the lead editor for that video
and that video was the opening video for
Kim cooks presentation keynote
presentation a couple years ago where
they rolled out Apple's new
accessibility website and their
accessibility features the other thing
is you guys may have seen Sadie during
the Superbowl she was one of the in
Superbowl commercial it was the Apple
commercial where they showed the stills
of all the famous people that used the
Mac so it was Oprah and Paul McCartney
and Bono and Malala and she was right
after Kermit the Frog but as an
assistive technology professional and
I've been doing assistive technology for
over thirty some years one of my job's
is to go into schools or into homes and
do assistive technology evaluations and
a lot and my evaluations really focused
on finding solutions for students to be
able to access the curriculum to access
their daily living and to access maybe
some communication well one of the
things that I always felt was missing
was the focus on finding tools that will
allow kids and young adults to express
themselves artistically that all changed
when I met Sadie when people look at me
most see a young woman with cerebral
palsy they see my disability but they
don't see me for who I really am they
don't see my ability they don't see the
passionate intelligent and independent
woman
that I
they don't see me for the artist I am I
am a video editor who uses video to tell
the story of how technology he can open
up the world for persons of all
abilities so they can access their
artists place in so we really live in an
exciting time because today's technology
you really gives us the power to put a
paintbrush into the hands of an artist
who can't hold a paintbrush or put give
the opportunity for someone who's blind
to become a photographer or the ability
to be able to put into the hands of a
musician an instrument when that
musician can't hold an instrument maybe
can't read or write music and the
ability to be able to put video editing
tools into control of a person who can't
use a traditional keyboard or Mouse when
I was younger I was really fascinated
with video editing I was fascinated by
the whole process of putting photos
together combining music and telling his
story
I loved how video could affect people's
emotions I wanted to learn how to do
this so Marc showed me the basics of
editing it was easy for me and I loved
it I spent several years doing videos
for weddings and the bursaries and
graduations I started a small business
where I continued to make videos but I
knew there was more that I could do and
I knew that there was so much more that
city could do I saw this young lady who
had a passion for film editing was
extremely talented and extremely
intelligent but I knew I had to find
another solution for her so I was at a
Institute and at Full Sail University in
Florida and for those of you don't know
who what Full Sail University is Full
Sail University is a university for
young adults who want to go into the
film industry into the music industry
into the gaming and the gaming design
industry well they had a program called
digital cinematography and it was an
online program so I talked to a couple
of the professors there and I said you
know what there's this amazingly
talented young lady back in north
that I would love does he go through
that program is there any way that we
can find a scholarship for her to be
able to go into digital cinematography
so they worked really hard in the
background and they were able actually
to secure her a full scholarship to
attend the online course for digital
cinematography it was an amazing
opportunity while I was attending Full
Sail I learned more about video editing
from my teachers who were working in the
film industry as a student I learned
about the whole process of making a film
and telling his story his skills helped
me to build my confidence and to refine
my skills I was able to produce better
films and became a much better editor my
goal was and is to create films that
help people understand disabilities and
to understand or realize their abilities
I want to showcase how accessible and
assistive technologies can create
opportunities for persons of all
abilities and how they can help them
realize their dreams as an artist I feel
I am just scratching the surface of my
ability and creativity but I also feel
that I have a platform and obligation to
spread a message of empowerment for all
I do that through video so Sadie
graduated with a degree in digital
cinematography but not only did she
graduate with a degree in digital
cinematography she graduated as one of
the top members of her class
in fact she got the advanced achievement
award now the beautiful thing about it
was is this was an online course and
because it was an online course no one
on the other hand knew that she had a
disability all they saw was her ability
not even her professors knew that she
had a disability all they were able to
see was the extreme talent and this
artist with an amazing amount of ability
technology is a huge part of my life and
I use it daily it's part of my DNA I
have every device you can think of an
Apple watch three computers and iPhone
and iPad and Apple TV and everything in
between but these devices alone or not
what empowers me it is what is being
built into these devices that empower
and enable me to access my world my
dreams in my inner artist accessibility
features such as switch control and
text-to-speech switch control gives me
full access to my devices text-to-speech
gives me my voice we really live in an
amazing time because a lot of the
assistive technologies and accessibility
features that are built into our devices
are available to all learners everyone
it levels that playing field it really
provides accessibility to a wide range
of users all over but to me it's really
more than accessibility it's accessing
abilities it's about finding those tools
that will allow artists to explore the
inner artist within and to become the
talented professionals like Sadie if
you're seeing me through the lens of my
disability it's not okay but I
understand it's human nature but don't
feel sorry for me I am here to help
change the narrative to change the
perception to tear down barriers and to
give you a different lens which to see
me through I will not do it by lecturing
people I will show you by being
example by telling stories through video
and with video so I asked you to see
beyond my disability and see my ability
see me as me intelligent passionate and
independent woman I am say the artist
within thank you
you